It's looking barren, but it's looking barren.
Looks like there's nothing there, because actually there is nothing here.
And we want to end up with something like that.
Um, okay.
So it's quite an involved website in the sense that it does have other aspects like emails and names,
but the basics of it are actually quite simple, and that's what we're going to focus on in this introductory
course on HTML.
So the basics are up here.
We've got sort of some sort of header.
And then if you look here we do have some sort of table with images in it.
So Josh what are we going to do to begin with.
Because this, this doesn't look like an H1.
No, no.
See if we go over it like with a mouse you can see.
Yeah you can highlight that.
So that's actually text.
But this doesn't that this here is not text and this image here.
And if you go into inspect you'll quickly discover it's not text.
So they've obviously created they've got a logo.
So that's what we want to do.
We want to go and create a logo that we're going to put at the top, and then put a table for some images.
So let's just get going with the basics.
So okay first of all we want to save our thing as an HTML file.
So we've opened a new tab.
We've gone come on in.
Come on.
Yeah.
So we now we command this okay.
So we're going to call this um okay.
Uh best cake site.
Yeah.
Don't remember.
We need to put the dot HTML.
Don't forget don't forget the dot HTML.
L m l m l.
We've got it.
Um, so now it knows.
It knows that this is going to not be a CSS or something else.
Crazy, right?
So what do we do next?
Do you remember h t m l tab and then we got, like, magic.
It all appears.
So it's already saying what's the title of the site?
I think we should put it in here.
The best.
So that's going to appear at the top, remember?
Best cake site.
Yeah.
Right.
So that's that's pretty, uh, simple.
So, uh, at the moment that's nothing too big a deal.
But what we're going to want to do when it comes to the logo, maybe we'll come back to that.
Let's just quickly set up the structure for our table that's going to put in the, uh, have the cake
pictures.
Yeah.
Okay.
So so that's going to go if we look um, at this like obviously you don't have to copy it particularly,
but it's quite nice to have they've got three by three and we'll just do like one, two three down.
So it's nine all together.
Yeah.
You can make as many as you want to do that.
We start with our table.
Table tag.
Yeah.
And then inside we've got our we've got three sets of TR.
So so we've got to make rows okay.
So we've got our rows.
And so there's going to be one.
And you can keep you.
Well let's make our three rows quickly.
Yeah.
Not your table.
And another are we Yeah, three rows.
Right.
So three rows.
And then within each row we've got three um TDs which is our table.
Okay.
Which is basically our column.
So there's going to be three columns within each row.
Yeah.
Okay.
Too easy.
So there's another column and there's another column.
Yeah.
So basically we could just copy that.
Just paste it in and we're going to stick it inside each of our rows.
Yeah.
Too easy.
Okay.
So we'll pop that in there.
And we need one more just over here.
And life is going to be just perfect.
So perfect little setup.
What we've got is our table.
You can see starting over there ending there.
And we've got row one, row two and row three.
And within each row we're going to have three columns.
Yeah.
So that's going to be nice and easy three by three.
Okay.
So let's uh save it shall we.
Go and have a look at it.
It's not going to be too much to see, but let's just get it open into our browser.
is my best cake site.
Yep.
And we open that with Chrome.
And there she goes.
She is absolutely nothing there.
Okay, so obviously you can't see the table.
All you can see is we've given it a name.
Uh, if you remember, we could go and view the page source and then you would see there is everything,
but there's nothing in the columns and in the rows, so nothing at the moment.
But that's cool.
Uh, we've got the basics of what we want.
Right?
So let's, um, we could use H1.
Yeah.
You remember that H1, but we could just put as part of the body.
Uh, just to give you a little taste of what that would taste.
Um.
That's amazing.
Uh, we could have done this and said the best cake site, which is, you know, it's not bad.
I wouldn't call it the best cake site.
Yeah, that's not going to be the best cake site, but there we got the best cake site.
You know, that's I mean, that's okay, but I mean, like, there's this cooler over here.
You know, they've got, like, uh, it looks like a.
what would you say?
It's got that like.
You know what?
How would you put that?
It's got that.
It just looks better than that one.
Yeah.
Yeah, it looks better than a little bit.
So what we got to do is we got to you.
Maybe you want to have your own logo.
You can.
And we're going to quickly show you this is extra.
No extra cost for this.
Nothing.
You can make your own logo.
I mean, you really you don't have to go out and get some expensive person.
There's lots of ways of doing this.
We're going to quickly show you how rather than having the best cakes out, you can create your own
logo.
So here's just one website you literally could do this in.
You could use PowerPoint to make your own logo.
You do what you like.
The bottom line is you've got to end up with an image.
And so we're just going to quickly show you free logo designs.
How you could do it quickly here.
Okay.
So you can see we've got all of these things to create my logo.
So yeah I'm going to create a logo for our cake site.
So we just go on and click click create logo on free logo 9.org.
And it just thinks for a while.
And all the clever elves who are inside the system are getting together.
Okay, so what are we going to pick here?
Let's see.
It's cakey.
I don't know what cakey it looks like.
Pizza ish.
No.
Um.
Let's see.
There's, like, millions of themes.
Oh, my.
There's even food and drink.
There's food and drink.
169 food and drink wines.
Oh, let's see if we can find one that has a burger.
Ooh, this one looks okay.
There's, like, cakey.
That's.
That's pretty close already.
Yeah.
So this one should do.
Okay.
So you just click on it and there it brings it through.
So now we can say what easy cake.
So what do we call it.
The best cake.
We don't really have.
Okay.
So we're just going to call ourselves the best cakes.
Yeah.
Just the best cakes.
The best cakes.
It's very original.
Okay, so all it's done.
I mean, you can move things around.
You can drop it slightly.
Uh, you can change the pictures, move them around.
We're not going to fiddle too much.
This is, uh, it's not a editing course.
This is just showing you how you can do it.
Okay.
Lovely little logo.
That's beautiful.
Uh, so you can add more shapes.
You can figure this out.
This is like, you don't have to be a rocket scientist to do this.
Yeah, so it seems pretty straightforward.
We've got our little.
Are you happy with the colors?
You're happy?
Yeah.
Everything's.
We don't have to be too picky on this.
Um, yeah, I can see there's lots of elements in this.
Um, okay, so we're just going to leave it like that.
As you see, we've got a little save option, so.
Okay, so this is the essence of this whole thing.
At the end of the day, whatever you're using, whatever designer, even if you're using PowerPoint,
you need to save it to a JPEG or a PNG file.
Uh, money money money.
But no, no money needed.
If you're going to take the low res 200 by 200.
Yeah, that's probably okay.
Just for a little logo for us.
Okay.
So okay, so once you've run the gauntlet and put in your email, While they are hopefully going to
send you a link to where you can get your free logo.
So we're going to go and have a look and see if we can find that on the other side.
Grab our logo right so you can see there it is a it sent us an email with our little logo that is looks
so cool.
And so we can now finally download that and get the image that we are so desperately require for our
website.
Right?
So now we've got to save this in a suitable spot where everything else is stored.
So we're just going to drop it in here with all our other files.
So it's good to keep everything in one spot.
And so it's now saved that in that folder.
So if we go in that folder we're going to see we've got our various sites and we've also got little
PNG file.
And there it is.
So we've got our logo.
It's just a little low res logo but it's there.
And now we can use it uh in our website.
So the point is you can create a logo however you like.
Um, in this example we've used free logo design.
There are lots of these things.
You just Google it, find one that suits you.
As we said, just go and create one in an edit and some editor.
You can even create one in PowerPoint, keynote, etc...
So there's our logo.
Uh, what's next is we want to get that logo inserted.
So rather than this boring sort of H1 thing here that's not so interesting.
Josh, take it away.
Let's get that inserted as an image logo.
Okay.
So we can actually put this in the head because it is a logo.
So that is one thing you can also do.
So we go img tab it.
And now it's got a space for our image.
So now if we just grab our logo here see.
Okay so we're not actually using an online logo.
Now remember if you had to publish this website online while this website is going to work locally,
if you had to publish online, that image would have to be stored online somewhere.
I'll refresh that.
We've got our little logo.
Oh, so there's our logo that looks much better.
So all that Josh has done is grabbed the image, which is stored locally in that same folder as best
case HTML.
So another way also to get this image.
See if we if we had renamed this we wouldn't.
Yeah that image.
So we just go here we can say open width.
Now if we say open with chrome you'll see it.
This is a it shows us Dropbox users Greg Blewett.
So if we save that again it's giving you the full path to it.
Yeah.
So um, this is also another way you could go command C, replace this with that.
And now we save this.
Go back there.
You'll see it's going to be the same.
Okay.
So the first time we put it in without the path what it's going to do is it's just going to look in
the current folder.
So it's going to look in the folder where HTML is.
If we rename this if we had just said okay.
Yeah.
Or if that was in another folder, it's not going to find it.
Okay.
So now if we had it like that command save refresh that there's going to be bad.
It's going to be bad.
There's nothing.
Yeah.
So we could just update the name.
So if we go back to finder, we open this again with Chrome.
You can get the full path again.
Yeah.
So it's actually better to rather than have a random name like we had there before.
Uh, what is that, nine, six seven?
That's ridiculous.
To give it a name that's vaguely understandable.
So when you do read your code, you know, okay, that's my cake image, you know, cake logo or something.
So give it a name that's sensible.
And obviously now you should be able to see it appear once again inside our website.
Right.
So that's pretty simple.
So we've covered the basics.
We've got our best cake site up and running.
We've got a title.
We've got a nice little logo in there.
And we've set up the table.
So ready we're ready to take it on okay.
So you know what you've got to do.
Go and eat a piece of cake and set up your basic skeleton for your cake website.